The Philip Mackie Collection
The Philip Mackie Collection
- Literary Papers, 1952 - 1985; 1999; MAC/1; Solent University Library; Mackie Philip 1918-1985; 151 boxes (11.5 metres) plus scattered items
  - The Girl at the Next Table [TV], approximately 1957; MAC/1/25; Solent University Library; 3 items
    1 typewritten draft script with compliments slip from the BBC attached.
    2 rehearsal draft scripts (one of them its cover torn).
    Held in boxes 33
    IMDB page for The Girl at the Next Table
  - The Hole in the Wall, 1955; MAC/1/80; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two camera scripts for The Hole in the Wall, a television play by Mackie that was broadcast by the BBC on September 22, 1955.
    Held in box 141
    IMDB page for The Hole in the Wall
  - The Inheritance, 1970; MAC/1/57; Solent University Library; 4 items
    Papers relating to The Inheritance, a screenplay by Philip Mackie based on an adaptation by Hugh Leonard of L'héritage, a short story by Guy de Maupassant. One script is dated 1970 and labelled "Granada Films Limited", so appears to be a proposed film that was not produced. Probably it is based on the episode The Inheritance of the 1963 Granada TV series Maupassant, which Mackie produced.
    Box 120: Scripts.
    Box 143: Handwritten notes in notebook.
    Held in boxes 120, 143
    IMDB page for The Inheritance [Related work]
  - The Liars, 1965 - 1966; MAC/1/1; Solent University Library; Leonard Hugh 1926-2009; 5 boxes
    Papers relating to The Liars, a 1966 Granada TV series of 13 episodes, featuring stories from a range of authors, adapted by Philip Mackie and Hugh Leonard.
    Box 43: (6 items) - 5 scripts of the Liars with handwritten corrections and 1 notebook (Mackie's)
    Box 44: (9 items) - various camera scripts, issued between Sept. 1965 to Jan 1966.
    Box 45: (6 items) - rehearsal scripts for the Liars
    Box 46: (8 items) - various draft camera scripts for the Liars
    Box 47: (10 items) - camera scripts for the Liars
    Held in boxes 43-47.
    IMDB page for The Liars
  - The Limbo Connection, 1976 - 1978; MAC/1/31; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to The Limbo Connection, a six-part dramatization of the novel of the same name by Derry Quinn, which was made for Thames Television and broadcast as part of the Armchair Theatre series in 1978.
    Box 48 (10 items) - 7 rehearsal scripts and two letters (a letter from Robert Banks Stewart (Thames Television), a re-cap of discussions on the six episodes of The Limbo Connection; a reply from Mackie); 1 page of the cast list (episodes 1-6).
    Box 82 - Handwritten notes in notebook.
    Box 126 - Correspondence with Andrew Brown, Thames TV, about the possibility of Mackie adapting The Limbo Connection.
    Box 143 (6 items) - 6 copies of rehearsal scripts for The Limbo Connection
    Held in boxes 48, 49, 82, 143
    IMDB page for The Limbo Connection
  - The Money, 1961; MAC/1/70; Solent University Library; 1 box
    Scripts for The Money ,a television play by Mackie that was broadcast on the BBC in 1961.
    Held in box 151
    IMDB page for The Money
  - The Naked Civil Servant, 1971 - 1975; MAC/1/35; Solent University Library; approximately 12 items
    Papers relating to The Naked Civil Servant, a 1975 Thames TV dramatization, by Mackie, of The Autobiography of Quentin Crisp (1968).
    Box 60: 1 copy of a draft screenplay (141 pages)
    Box 61: 4 copies of draft screenplays; an outline of Jack Gold's studio days, location and budget estimates (some handwritten).
    Box 126: Correspondence relating to The Naked Civil Servant, including a rejection from Mike Wooller at the BBC (1974).
    Box 146: Two copies of documents showing the provisional and final cast list and proposed rehearsal schedule for The Naked Civil Servant.
    Held in boxes 60 - 61; 126; 146
    IMDB page for The Naked Civil Servant
  - The Night Nurse, or, Hospital, 1975 - 1985; MAC/1/6; Solent University Library; approximately 10 items
    Papers relating to The Night Nurse, a teleplay by Mackie that appears never to have been produced.
    2 scripts for "The Night Nurse", one dated 4/9/85.
    Correspondence (1975-1976) between Mackie and Irene Shubik, of BBC TV, relating to revisions for The Hospital, which is evidently an earlier working title for The Night Nurse.
    Held in boxes 2 and 126.
    Shubik Irene 1929-2019
  - The Omega Factor, approximately 1978; MAC/1/66; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A script of The Undiscovered Country. Part Four by Philip Mackie. This appears to be a script prepared for the 1979 BBC TV series The Omega Factor, though as Mackie receives no writing credit for that series, it is probable that Mackie's contribution was never used.
  - The Organization, 1971 - 1974; MAC/1/44; Solent University Library; 5 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to The Organization - a 1972 Yorkshire Television series written by Mackie, and to its novelization, published in 1974.
    Box 83: 6 copies of camera scripts for episodes 4-6
    Box 84: 6 copies of camera scripts for episodes 1-3
    Box 85: Typescript of The Organization, a novelization of the TV series by Philip Mackie.
    Box 86: Revision notes (4 pages) for episodes 1 and 2
    Box 88: 7 copies of rehearsal scripts for episodes 4-7; a letter (a handwritten draft and typewritten) to James Ormerod (dated 25 Jan 1972) about script corrections and amendments regarding episode 5.
    Box 89: 7 copies of earlier versions of scripts relating to the seven episodes of The Organization (1971)
    Box 126: A draft paperback cover and blurb for the fiction The Organisation that was sent to Mackie from the publisher Quartet Books Limited. The paperback was published by Quartet Books on July 22, 1974. Correspondence related to this novelization by Dulan Barber.
    Box 143: A notebook containing notes on The Organization.
    Held in boxes 83-86; 88-89; 126; 143
    IMDB page for The Organization
  - The Revenger's Tragedy, 1964; MAC/1/30; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Typewritten script for a dramatization, by Mackie, of The Revenger's Tragedy (attributed to Cyril Tourneur). The script appears to have been prepared for TV in the same way, and at roughly the same time, as Women Beware Women and The Changeling, but there is no external reference to help determine if this was ever broadcast.
    Held in box 42
  - The Ribadier System [Theatre], MAC/1/82; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A bound, typewritten script of The Ribadier System, a translation and adaptation - for the stage - by Philip Mackie of the farce by Georges Feydeau.
    Held in box 149.
  - The Rich are Different, 1981 - 1982; MAC/1/81; Solent University Library; approximately 7 items
    Papers relating to The Rich are Different, Mackie's dramatization of Susan Howatch's novel of the same name. It appears the dramatization was never produced.
    - Two copies of outline treatment for episodes 2-13
    - Two copies of scripts relating to episode 1 of The Rich are Different
    - Correspondence with Verity Lambert (Thames TV) about the possibility of producing the series [Box 128].
    Held in boxes 128 and 144
  - The Right Person, 1954; MAC/1/69; Solent University Library; 5 items
    Scripts for The Right Person, a teleplay by Philip Mackie that was broadcast on BBC TV in 1954.
    IMDB page for The Right Person
  - The Rivals of Sherlock Holmes. Madame Sara, approximately 1971; MAC/1/90; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Notes relating to Madame Sara, an episode written by Mackie from the Thames TV series The Rivals of Sherlock Holmes, broadcast on ITV in two series, 1971 and 1973. Madame Sara was broadcast in 1971.
    Held in box 143.
    IMDB page for Madame Sara
  - The Shadow of Ignorance, 1960; MAC/1/83; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Papers relating to The Shadow of Ignorance, a documentary intended to inform the public about Venereal Disease, made by Granada TV and broadcast in 1960. Mackie is credited under "programme prepared by ...".
    Detailed contents: a script and a transcript.
  - The She-Wolves, 1983 - 1985; MAC/1/52; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to The She-Wolves, a dramatization, by Mackie, of the 1955 novel Les Louves by Boileau-Narcejac. It was never produced, though a version was made with a different writer under the title Letters to an Unknown Lover.
    Two complete copies of scripts for The She-Wolves (1984).
    Correspondence with Ian Warren (1983-1985) regarding working title and script changes for The She-Wolves and the eventual production of Letters to an Unknown Lover.
    An outline and synopses for The She-Wolves.
    A clipping from The Times Monday Sept 9, 1983.
    Held in box 113, 129, 130 and new box 4 at the end of Mackie's collection
  - The Smiths of London, 1952; MAC/1/73; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Shooting script for The Smiths of London, also given the handwritten title Housewife, to be made at Cinetone Studios. The work is described as a 'half-hour TV show', but appears to be a film of the kind made for the Ministry of Information, Films Division, for whom Mackie worked.
    Held in box 137
  - The Whiteoak Chronicles, 1954 - 1955; MAC/1/58; Solent University Library; 11 items
    Scripts for The Whiteoak Chronicles, four teleplays by Mackie, based on the Whiteoak novel series by Mazo de la Roche (also known as the Jalna series). The teleplays were broadcast by the BBC in 1954-1955, the first three as part of the Sunday-Night Theatre anthology series.
    Episode list, in order of broadcast:
    - The Whiteoak Chronicles: Young Renny
    - The Whiteoak Chronicles: Whiteoak Heritage
    - The Whiteoak Chronicles: Jalna
    - The Whiteoak Chronicles: Whiteoaks, possibly based on the novel which is also known as Whiteoaks of Jalna.
    Box 121: Four copies of rehearsal scripts for Young Renny (1954) and Jalna (1955).
    Box 122: Two copies of rehearsal scripts and a draft script for Whiteoak Heritage (1955).
    Box 123: Three copies of rehearsal scripts for Whiteoaks (1955).
    Unnumbered box (Mackie Spare Box #1): A copy of a rehearsal script and a draft script for Jalna
    Held in boxes 121-123; Unnumbered box (Mackie Spare Box #1)
    IMDB page for The Whiteoak Chronicles: Young Renny
    IMDB page for The Whiteoak Chronicles: Whiteoak Heritage
    IMDB page for The Whiteoak Chronicles: Jalna
    IMDB page for The Whiteoak Chronicles: Whiteoaks
  - The Whole Truth, 1955 - 1956; MAC/1/11; Solent University Library; 4 boxes
    Papers relating to The Whole Truth, a drama by Philip Mackie. It was originally produced as a teleplay for BBC TV (1955), and reworked for stage by 1956, with an edition published. The play was later made into a film directed by John Guillermin (1958), and it appears that another version, called Death of a Guest, was broadcast by the BBC in 1960.
    Box 124: Draft scripts for the 1955 teleplay The Whole Truth, including handwritten notes, corrections, and a message for Stephen Harrison, the director. These scripts are titled Death of a Guest, and Mackie also noted on the cover an alternative title, Against the Evidence.
    Boxes 6 and 125: Four bound copies of scripts for The Whole Truth, all dated January 1956 and apparently the revised (theatre) version.
    Box 136: Revision notes and cast list for The Whole Truth. A letter to Stephen Harrison, signed simply 'Bob', that appears to answer questions about the accuracy of police procedure depicted in the TV drama.
    Held in boxes 6, 124, 125 & 136
    IMDB page for the 1955 BBC TV play The Whole Truth
    IMDB page for the 1958 Columbia Pictures film The Whole Truth [Related work].
    IMDB page for the 1960 BBC TV play Death of a Guest [Related work].
  - Thérèse Raquin, 1978 - 1980; MAC/1/54; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to Thérèse Raquin, a three-part dramatisation of the novel of the same name by Emile Zola, which was made for The BBC and broadcast in 1980.
    Box 116: Six copies of revised and rehearsal scripts for parts 1-3
    Box 117: Three copies of draft rehearsal scripts for parts 1-3; various letters between Mackie and Betty Willingale (BBC TV), and a map of BBC TV rehearsal rooms
    Box 104: A promotional document produced by the BBC and presumably distributed to the press.
    Box 127: Correspondence between Mackie and Jonathan Powell and Betty Willingale (BBC TV) discussing scripts and casting.
    Held in boxes 104, 116 & 117, 127
    IMDB page for Thérèse Raquin
  - They Called Me Al: The Life of Al Bowlly, 1979 - 1980; MAC/1/8; Solent University Library; Colin Sid 1920-1989; 2 boxes
    Papers relating to They Called Me Al: The Life of Al Bowlly, a dramatization of the life of the musician Al Bowlly that appears never to have been produced.
    Draft scripts by Mackie for They Called Me Al: The Life of Al Bowlly.
    A treatment for a dramatisation of Al Bowlly's life by Sid Colin, dated March 1979. There is also a letter from Colin explaining that this was written as part of drafting his biography of Bowlly.
    Various press cuttings and interviews relating to Bowlly.
    Various letters and postcard exchanges related to this work, including memoirs of Bowlly by those who knew him, clearly solicited by Mackie for the purposes of preparing the screenplay. There is also correspondence with Euston Films Ltd., who appear to have been interested in producing the dramatization.
    Held in boxes 3 and 128
    Bowlly Albert Alick 1899-1941; Colin Sid 1920-1989
  - Thirteen Against the Bank, approximately 1970; MAC/1/55; Solent University Library; 1 box plus scattered items
    Papers relating Thirteen Against the Bank, a dramatization by Mackie of Norman Leigh's novel. It seems the dramatization was never produced.
    Various copies of scripts for episodes 1-6.
    Correspondence with David Reid (ATV) [1979-1980] about the possibility of producing the series.
    Held in boxes 118 and 127-128.
  - Thou Shalt Not Kill, 1957; MAC/1/63; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A script for Thou Shalt Not Kill, a discussion programme about euthanasia which was made by Granada TV and broadcast on 25 June 1957. The script includes verbatim or suggested comments for the host, Robin Day, and contributors, and also some mini-plays illustrating the issues. Mackie's role is unclear, possibly he contributed to the script, or perhaps was a producer.
  - Victorian Villainies. In the Fog, 1985; MAC/1/22; Solent University Library; Markstein George 1929-1987; approximately 6 items
    Papers relating to In the Fog, a draft screenplay by Mackie of In the Fog, adapted from the story of the same name by Richard Harding Davis. Victorian Villainies (note that the title page has a misprint: "Victorian Villanies") seems to be a series title, and it may well have been intended to be an anthology series of Victorian crime stories. It appears that neither series nor episode were ever produced. The series was probably inspired by the publication of The Penguin Book of Victorian Villainies in 1984, which included In the Fog.
    Two copies of a draft script.
    Correspondence between Mackie and George Markstein, Thames TV, in which they disagree at length over the form the screenplay should take before deciding to abandon the project.
    Held in boxes 25, 110, and 130.
    Markstein George 1929-1987
  - Women Beware Women, 1964; MAC/1/28; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Typewritten script for a dramatization, by Mackie, of Thomas Middleton's Women Beware Women broadcast as part of ITV's Play of the Week on 11 January 1965.
    IMDB page for Women Beware Women
- Personal Papers, 1947 - 1990; MAC/2; Solent University Library; 12 boxes (1 metre) plus scattered items
  Personal papers of Philip Mackie, including diaries, financial papers, and newspaper cuttings related to his writing.
  - Correspondence, approximately 1954 - 1985; MAC/2/5; Solent University Library; Crisp Quentin 1908-1999; approximately 200 items
    Various personal letters and correspondences of Philip Mackie. As well as correspondence with friends and family, it includes letters from the public and colleagues praising, occasionally criticising, his work, sometimes with Mackie's response. There are particularly large collections of these letters for The Caesars, East Lynne, and The Naked Civil Servant.
    Includes correspondence with Quentin Crisp, twelve letters between 1975 and 1980, some with Mackie's response.
    Other notable correspondents include:
    Lois Garner (Mrs James Garner); Sam Rosenberg; Andre Morell; Lord Sidney Bernstein; Arnold Goldman.
    Held in boxes 103-104 and 126-130
    Correspondence relating to the production of specific works (e.g., about re-writes, casting, shooting schedules etc.) is mentioned in the description of those works under Literary Papers.
    Correspondence relating to contracts, payments, and other financial matters is mentioned under Finances.
    Crisp Quentin 1908-1999
  - Diaries, Address Book, and Passport, 1947 - 1985; MAC/2/1; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus 1 item
    Diaries for selected years between 1963 and 1985, an address book, and a passport used between 1947 and 1952. The diaries mainly record appointments and are sparsely filled. There is also a notebook containing (in addition to writing notes) a detailed record of Mackie's a one week stay at Grayshott Hall, a health spa in Surrey.
    The diaries, address book, and passport are in two unnumbered boxes labelled "Diaries" at the end of the collection.
    The notebook with details of the stay at Grayshott Hall is in box 43.
  - Finances and Property, 1957 - 1990; MAC/2/2; Solent University Library; 8 boxes plus scattered items
    Certificates, statements, correspondence, and other documents relating to Mackie's finances: insurance, pensions, income, and bank accounts. In addition there is corresponence relating to the legal and financial side of the lease on Philip Mackie's London flat and the ownership of Siddington Old Rectory and its associated land, including correspondence with the Bathurst Estate about the boundaries of the respective properties.
    Held in boxes 2; 126-130; 131b; three unnumbered boxes labelled "Insurance, Pensions", "Finances 77-79" and "Finances 79-82".
  - Newspaper Clippings and Pamphlets, 1981 - 1986; MAC/2/4; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus scattered item
    Various press clippings relating to Philip Mackie's life and works, principally clippings of reviews concerning several of Mackie's works. There are two formal obituaries of Mackie and two posthumous articles about him, all pasted onto one sheet. There are also pamphlets and promotional materials relating to Mackie's works.
    Held in boxes 86, 103, 104.